<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A call unto the seed of Israel that they may come out of Egypts darkness and house of bondage unto the land of rest : also the righteous law of God justified : with an epistle to all those whose desire are after the truth as it is in Jesus where ever they are scattered : also twenty five queries to all the worlds priests and people that say the light of Christ is natural / by M.F.</title>
            <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41050</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">9527176</idno>
  <idno type="VID">43480</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248501341</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26706</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">09527176</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41050)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43480)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1331:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A call unto the seed of Israel that they may come out of Egypts darkness and house of bondage unto the land of rest : also the righteous law of God justified : with an epistle to all those whose desire are after the truth as it is in Jesus where ever they are scattered : also twenty five queries to all the worlds priests and people that say the light of Christ is natural / by M.F.</title>
                  <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1668?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Inner Light.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43480:1"/>
            <p>A CALL UNTO THE Seed of Israel, THAT They may come out of <hi>EGYPTS Darkness,</hi> and House of Bondage, unto the Land of Rest.</p>
            <p>ALSO The Righteous Law of God Justified.</p>
            <p>WITH An <hi>EPISTLE</hi> to all those, whose desire are after the <hi>TRƲTH,</hi> as it is in <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SƲS,</hi> where ever they are <hi>Scattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO Twenty five <hi>QƲERIES</hi> to all the Worlds <hi>PRIESTS</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> that say, <hi>the Light of CHRIST is Natural.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>M. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilson.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:43480:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43480:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A CALL unto the Seed of</hi> ISRAEL, <hi>that they may come out of</hi> Egypts Darkness, <hi>and House of Bondage, into the Land of Rest,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>AWake, awake, put on thy strength <hi>O SION,</hi> put on thy beautiful Garments, <hi>O JERƲSALEM,</hi> the Holy City: For henceforth, there shall no more come unto thee, The uncircumcised, and the unclean. Shake thy self from the dust, arise and sit down, <hi>O Jerusalem;</hi> loose thy self from the bands of thy neck, <hi>O Captive Daughter</hi> of <hi>Sion;</hi> for thus faith the Lord, <hi>Yee have sold your selves for nought, and yee shall be redeemed without many,</hi> Isa. 52.1, 2, 3. Now is the free Covenant of everlasting life set open to you, which brings Salvation unto the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Therefore O house of <hi>Jacob</hi> come yee, and let us walk in the Light of the Lord, which is now shining in this his day; gloriously is the Lord ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen, and shining in the consciences of men; in him is life, and the life is the light of men; this is he which <hi>Isaiah</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied of, which is now fulfilled, who said, <hi>Ho every one that thirsteth, come yee to the waters, and he that hath no mony, come yee, buy, and eat, yea come buy wine, and milk, without mony, and without price;</hi> and <hi>JESƲS CHRIST,</hi> who is the Fountain, cryed, saying, <hi>If any man thirst, let him come to me and drink, he that believeth on me,</hi> (as the Scripture hath said) <hi>out of his belly shall flow Rivers of living water,</hi> but this he spake of the Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 7.37, 38. and this is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, which <hi>Moses</hi> saw, and told <hi>Israel</hi> of, God is thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and underneath are the everlasting arms, he shall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43480:3"/>thrust out the enemy before thee, and shall destroy them; <hi>Israel</hi> then shall dwell in safty alone, the fountain of <hi>Jacob</hi> shall be upon a land of Corn, and Wine, also his Heavens shall drop down dew: Happy art thou O <hi>Israel!</hi> who is like unto thee, a people saved by the Lord, the sheild of thy help! and who is the Sword of thy Excellency, and thine enemies shall be found lyars unto thee, and thou shall tread upon the high places of the earth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.27, 28, 29. Now is this fulfilled, in all who turn to the light, which comes from the life, which is the fountain, which is now set open for all Nations to flow unto, and all the Nations that are saved, walk in the light of the Lamb: <hi>David</hi> saw this, when he said, <hi>How excellent is thy loving kindnesse O God, therefore the children of men put their trust under the shadow of thy wings, they shall be abundantly satisfied with the fatnesse of thy house, and thou shalt make them drink, with the Rivers of thy pleasures, for with thee is the Fountain of Life; in thy Light, we see Light,</hi> Psal 36.7, 8, 9. Therefore did he say, <hi>Tremble thou earth, at the presence of the Lord, at the presence of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>which turned the Rock into a standing water, and the flint into a Fountain of water,</hi> Psal. 104.8. and the day is come that <hi>Zachariah</hi> saw, who saith, In that day there shall be a Fountain open, to the house of <hi>David,</hi> and to the Inhabitants of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> for sin, and for uncleanness, and it shall come to passe in that day, saith the Lord of Hosts; that I will cut off the name of the Idolls out of the Land, and they shall be no more remembred; and also, I will cause the Prophets, and the unclean spirits, to passe out of the Land, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1.2. and this is fulfilled, praises to the living God; and the true Prophet is risen, which <hi>Moses</hi> said, the Lord will raise, who teacheth his people himself, in whom is life, and this life is the light of men, whose Name is the Lord our Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse, and whose Light leads unto Righteousness, and Purity, and whose blood washeth and cleanseth from all sin, all that believe, and obey the gospel; And the day is come which <hi>Joel</hi> prophesied of, who said, <hi>the Lord also shall roar out of</hi> Sion, <hi>and utter his voice from</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>and the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the Earth shall shake, but the Lord will be the hope of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43480:3"/>his people, and the strength of the children of</hi> Israel; <hi>so shall yee know that I am the Lord your God, dwelling in</hi> Sion, <hi>my holy Mountain: then shall</hi> Jerusalem <hi>be holy, and there shall no stranger passe through her any more, and it shall come to passe in that day, that the Mountains shall drop down new wine, and the hills shall flow with milk, and all the Rivers of</hi> Judah <hi>shall flow with water, and a Fountain shall come forth out of the House of the Lord, and shall water the valleys,</hi> Joel 3.16, 17, 18. but to all the stif-necked, and uncircumcised in hearts, and ears, who are dissobedient to their measures, unto them this Fountain is sealed, my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved is as a spring shut up, and as a Fountain sealed, and yet he is as a Fountain of Gardens, and a well-spring of living waters, and streams from <hi>Lebanon,</hi> unto the faithful and obedient, who wait in the Light, for his appearance, the second time without sin; and this, all the faithful and obedient shall witnes: And therefore all that desire to know the living God, who desires to have living vertue, and grace unto your Soules, wait in the Light, which shines in your Consciences, for this fountain of life, is the light of men, and there is no life to be found but in the Fountain, which is now set open, for the gathering of all Nations to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, by his Light which gathers together into one, which is the Covenant, which is given a light to the Gentiles, which brings salvation the ends of the earth, and this yee shall eternally witness to be truth. Therefore as you love your Souls, turn to the Light, and fear the Lord God; for <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, <hi>The fear of the Lord is a Fountain of life,</hi> and again he saith, <hi>The law of the wise is a Fountain of life, and the the Law of God endures for ever,</hi> God is pure, &amp; his law is pure, and the Word of the Lord endures for ever, who said, <hi>I am the Lord thy God, which brought thee out of the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>from the house of Bondage,</hi> this endures for ever, the same Lord brings from <hi>Egypt,</hi> and out of the house of Bondage still.</p>
            <p>Therefore, all people, high and low, rich and poor, <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Barbarian, Scythian,</hi> minde the Light, by which the Lord God calleth out of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Sodom,</hi> which is all the world Spiritually, where our Lord is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified; By this light, which is the life of the Law, doth he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43480:4"/>call the seed out of Bondage still, for <hi>Moses</hi> saw this, when he said, And he came with ten-thousand of his Saints, from his right hand went a fiery law for them, yea, he loved the people, all his Saints are in thy hand, and they sate down at thy feet, every one shall receive of thy words, <hi>Moses</hi> commanded us a Law, even the inheritance of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of <hi>Jacob, Deut.</hi> 33.2, 3, 4. and this inheritance endures for ever, who dwells and abides in this pure and perfect Law of God; the promise of God is anexed to this, even the sure mercies of <hi>David;</hi> and in this Law, did <hi>David</hi> meditate day and night, the Law of God was in his heart, <hi>Psal.</hi> 78. <hi>Give ear O my people unto my Law, incline your ears unto the Words of my Mouth. I will open my mouth in parables; I will utter dark sayings of old: Which we have heard &amp; known, and our fathers have told us. And we will not hide them from the children, shewing to the generation to come, the prayses of the Lord: and his Strength, and his wonderful works that he hath done. For he hath established a testimony in</hi> Jacob, <hi>and appointed a Law in</hi> Israel, <hi>when he commanded our fathers, that they should make them known to their children. That the generations to come might know them, even the children which should be born: who should arise and declare them to their children. That they might set their hope in God, and not forget the works of God: but keep his Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Law <hi>David</hi> beares witnesse to, and all that are of God, beares witness to this Law; for this was a Statute for <hi>Israel,</hi> and a Law for the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but they that were rebellious and stubborn; Children of <hi>Ephraim</hi> they kept not the Covenant of God, and refused to walk in his laws; and so it is still; The Lord complains of the Idol Shepherds, My people are destroyed for lack of knowledge; because thou hast rejected knowledge, I will also reject thee, thou shalt be no Priest unto me, seeing thou hast forgotten the law of thy God, I will also forget thy children. Now let all people try, and search, whether all the Priests, and Teachers, of this Nation of <hi>England,</hi> or elsewhere, have not quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten this Law, and cast it behind their backs, and call the righteous Law of God, which endures for ever, which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43480:4"/>the Apostle said was spirituall, holy, just, and good, this they call a Covenant of works, and say Christ hath abol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished it, which is contrary to Christs own words, who said, <hi>Think not that I am come to destroy the Law, I am not come to destroy, but to fulfill; for verily I say unto you, till heaven and earth passe, one jott, or tittle, shall in no wise passe from the law, till all be fulfilled, Math.</hi> 5.17, 18. and when one of the <hi>Pharisees,</hi> who was a <hi>Lawyer,</hi> asked Christ a question, saying Master, <hi>which is the greatest Commandement in the Law?</hi> Jesus said unto him, <hi>Thou shalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, with all thy soul, and with all thy mind: this is the first and great Commandement,</hi> and the second is like unto it, <hi>Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thy self; on these two hang all the Law, and the Prophets.</hi> Here Christ Jesus, who is the end of the Law, for righteousesse, witnesseth to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous law of God, which <hi>Moses</hi> taught <hi>Israel;</hi> who said, Hear O <hi>Israel,</hi> the Lord our God, is one Lord, and thou shalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy might; and these words, which I command thee this day shall be in thy heart, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6. Here now the oneness of the Lord is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest, who hath sent his onely begotten Son, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy, but to fulfill this Law, which is one; And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle saith, that he was alive without the law, but when the Commandement came, sin revived, and he dyed, and yet he was touching the law blameless. Now see if any of ye blind Pharisees of <hi>England,</hi> can expound this, who deny the Law of God, and cast it behind your backs; the Apostle saith, he that sins without the Law, shall perish with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Law; &amp; as many as have sinned under the Law, shall be judged by the Law: for not the hearers of the law shall be justified before God, but the doers of the law shall be justified. Now see where you will appeare; who have cast the righteous law of God behinde your back, and are no Ministers, neither of the Law, nor of the Gospell; for the Ministers of the Spirit, both under the Law, and Gospell, bear witness to the righteous Law of God, and walk in it, and fulfill it, by the strength and power of him, who is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43480:5"/>the end of the Law for righteousness, he that can receive it let him, <hi>for the Gentiles, which have not the law, do the things contained in the law, which shews the works of the law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their hearts, their consciences bearing them witness, in the day when God shall judge the secrets of men by Jesus Christ:</hi> This day is come; and your talking of Christ, and of a God, will not serve, who have cast the law of God behind your backs; and the secrets of your hearts, you come not to judge, but your covers are come to be rent off, and your nak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness will appear; For out of <hi>Sion,</hi> the law is going forth, and the word of the Lord from <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and <hi>Sion</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed thorough judgement, and her converts with righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, and the destruction of the transgressors, and of the sinners, shall be together, and they that forsake the Lord shall be consumed; for yee shall be ashamed of the Oakes, which yee have desired, and yee shall be confounded for the Gardens, which ye have chosen; and ye shall be as an Oak, whose lease fadeth, and as a garden, that hath no water, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.31. and the strong shall be as tow, and the maker of it, as a spark, and they shall both burn together, and none shall quench them: And this shall you Priests of <hi>Baal,</hi> and your upholders, eternally witnesse, for the last dayes are coming, and the Mountain of the Lords house is established upon the top of the Mountains, and it shall be exalted above the Hills, and people shall flow unto it, and many Nations shall come, and say, Come, and let us go up unto the mountain of the Lord, and to the house of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and he will teach us of his wayes, and we will walk in his paths, for the law shall go forth of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the word of the Lord from <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> and this is fulfilled, in this our day, glory, and praise, be to the Lord for ever. Hearken unto me, ye that know righteousness, the people in whose hearts, is my law, fear ye not the reproaches of men, neither be ye afraid of their revilings. For the moth shall eat them like a garment, and the worm shall eat them like wood; I but my righteousness shall be for ever, and my salvation from generation, to generation, <hi>Isa.</hi> 51.7, 8, 9. and the Lord saith by <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Thus saith the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43480:5"/>Lord, Stand in the Court of the Lords house, and speak unto all the Citties of <hi>Judah,</hi> which come to worship in the Lords house, all the words which I command thee to speak unto them, diminish not a word; and thou shalt say unto them, Thus saith the Lord, if ye will not hearken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, to walk in my Law, which I have set before you, and to hearken to the words of my Prophets, which I have sent unto you, then will I make this house, like unto <hi>SHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOH,</hi> and this Citty a curse, to all the Nations upon earth <hi>Jer.</hi> 26.4, 5, 6. Therefore beware all you Priests of <hi>BAAL,</hi> which cast the law of God behinde your backs; and the Lord saith, because they have forsaken my law, which I set before them, and have not obeyed my voyce neither walked therein, but have walked after the imaginations of their own hearts, and after <hi>Baalam,</hi> which their Fathers taught them; therefore thus saith the Lord of hosts, the God of <hi>Israel, Behold I will feed them even with worm-wood, and give them water of gall to drink, this ye shall be sure of, Jer.</hi> 9.13, 14. and the Lord saith by <hi>Zechariah,</hi> Yea they made their hearts as an Adamant stone least they should hear the Law, and the words, which the Lord of hosts sent, in his Spirit, by the former Prophets, therefore came a great wrath from the Lord of hosts: Therefore it is come to passe, that as he cryed, and they would not hear, so they cryed, and I would not heare, saith the Lord of hosts, <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.12, 13.</p>
            <p>Therefore all people as ye desire your souls peace and comfort, turn to the Law, written in your hearts, which the Lord hath put in your inward parts; that you may know him to be your God, and that you may be his people, that ye need not say, <hi>know the Lord, for all shall know him, from the least, unto the greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> When the Lord appeared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Abraham,</hi> he said unto him, <hi>I am the Almighty God, walk before me, and be thou perfect,</hi> here is a Law, and this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for ever; And he saith, I will make my covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and thee, and thy seed after thee, in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for an everlasting Covenant; to be a God unto thee, and thy Seed after thee, every man-child among you shall be <hi>Circumcised,</hi> Gen. 17.1. to the 12. <hi>And ye shall circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43480:6"/>the flesh of the foreskins, and it shall be a token of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant between me, and you,</hi> this is the Seale of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the <hi>Circumcision</hi> which is of the heart; and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle saith, <hi>he gave him the Covenant of Circumcision,</hi> Acts. 7.8. And again he saith, <hi>And he received the sign of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision, a seale of the Righteousnesse of the Faith which he had,</hi> yet being <hi>uncircumcised,</hi> that he might be the Father of all them that believe, though they be not circumcised out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. and we are the <hi>Circumcision,</hi> who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God in the Spirit, and have no considence in the flesh, and this is the seale of the Covenant, which stands for ever, unto all the seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to which the promise is: And except the Lord of the Sabbath, had left us a seed, we had been as SODOM, and been like unto GOMORRAH; what shall we say? then that the gentiles who followed not after righteousness, have attained to righteousness, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the righteousness, which is of faith; but <hi>Israel,</hi> who followed after the law of righteousness, hath not attained unto the law of righteousness, because they sought it not by faith, but as it were by the works of the law, for they stumbled at the stumbling stone, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.29, 30, 31, 32. And here do all the Builders and Pharises of this age stumble, who know not the Light; the Life of the law they dissalow, and set at naught the <hi>Corner stone,</hi> CHRIST JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS the LIGHT, who is the rock, upon which the whole Church is built, and by which <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> come to savlation; and this must needs be so, for it is written, <hi>Behold I lay in Sion a stumbling stone, a rock of offence, and whosoever believeth on him, shall not bee ushamed,</hi> and because of their stumbling and disalowing the Corner stone, CHRIST JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS the LIGHT, which is the first step into the way, the truth and the life; and none comes unto the Father but by him, and so long as they are out of this Way, and stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at the Light, they shall never know the true faith, nor they shall ever come to attain the law of righteousnes, because they do not seek it by the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, which is not holden with respect of persons, but is a mystery held in a pure conscience, which the defiled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43480:6"/>shall never know; And this ye shall eternally witness to be truth.</p>
            <p>Repent you therefore, and be converted, that your sins may be blotted out, when the time of refreshing shall come from the presence of the Lord; as saith the Apostle, and he shall send Jesus Christ, who before was preached unto you, whom the heavens must receive, untill the restitution of all things, which God hoth spoken by the mouth of all his holy Prophets, since the world began; for <hi>Moses</hi> said unto the Fathers, <hi>A Prophet shall the Lord raise up unto you, like unto me, him shall you hear in all things, whatsoever he shall say unto you, and it shall come to passe, that every soul, that will not heare this Prophet, shall be destroyed from among the people, Acts</hi> 3.22, 23. And now is this Prophet risen, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of men, and he is teaching his people by his Light, who is the Light of the world, and this is the condemnation of the world, that Light is come, and men love darkness, rather than light, because their deeds are evill: But from the Light, which shines in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences they cannot fly, but one day it shall find them out; all who hate it, it is their condemnation for ever, but as many as obey it, and walk in it, shall not walk in darkness, but have the Light of Life; yea all the Prophets from <hi>Samuel,</hi> and those that followed after as many as have spoken, have likewise foretold of these day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, ye are the children of the Prophets, and of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which God made with our Father; saying unto <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, And in thy Seed shall all the kindreds of the earth be blessed,</hi> unto you first, God having raised up his Son Jesus, sent him to blesse you, in turning away every one of you, from his iniquities, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.24, 25, 26. The Light of Jesus makes manifest sin and iniquity; and turns from the darkness to the Light, <hi>I the Lord have called thee in Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and will hold thine hand and will keep thee, and give thee for a Covenant to the people, for a Light to the Gentiles, to open the blind eyes, to bring out the Prisoners from the Prison, and them that sit in darknesse, out of the prison house.</hi> This is he that brings Salvation unto <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> who brings back
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43480:7"/>the Captivity, of the whole seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to which the promise is; who is anointed to preach glad tidings to the meek, who is sent to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lind up the broken hearted, to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim liberty to the Captives, Christ Jesus the Light, who is the everlasting Covenant, and Oath of God, is made a Priest for ever, <hi>after the order of</hi> MELCHISEDECK, <hi>King of</hi> Salem, <hi>Priest of the most high God,</hi> who met <hi>Abraham</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from the slaughter of the Kings, and blessed him, to whom also <hi>Abraham</hi> gave a tenth part of all; first being by Interpretation, <hi>King of Righteousnesse;</hi> and after that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Salem,</hi> which is King of peace; without Father, without Mother, without descent, having neither beginning of dayes, nor end of life, but made like unto the Son of God, abideth a Priest continually, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p>So all poor people <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> give over looking after your changeable Priests; for CHRIST JESUS the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changable is risen to teach his people, who is made a Priest with the Oath of God, which never can be revoked; but stands for evermore, for <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Barbarians, Scythians, Bond</hi> and <hi>Free,</hi> who hath taken down the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition wall betwixt us, and hath made of twain, one new man, as the Apostle saith, that the blessing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> might come on the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> through <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith; Now to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed were the promises made, he saith not to <hi>Seeds</hi> as of many, but as of one, and to thy <hi>Seed</hi> which is CHRIST: And this I say, that the Covenant which was confirmed before of God in Christ The Law which was four hundred and thirty years after cannot dissanul, that it should make the promise of none essect, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14, 16, 17. and this is the Seed which the Lord hath promised, shall be known among the Gentiles, and their off-spring among all people, and they that see them, shall acknowledge them, that they are the Seed, which God hath blessed: Therefore all people, as you desire the redemption of your Souls, turn to the light of Jesus Christ, which makes manifest your evil deeds, and the secret thoughts of your hearts, that they are vain; that is the light, by which the Lord teacheth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43480:7"/>his people, by which all the Seed of <hi>Israel, Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> shall be saved, as it is written, <hi>There shall come out of Sion, the Deliverer, and he shall turn away ungodlynesse from</hi> Jacob, <hi>and this is my Covenant unto them, when I shall take away their sins,</hi> Rom. 11.26, 27. So do not deceive your Souls; no Covenant but where the sins is taken away, they who are strangers from the life, are aliens to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of the promise; And where there is not the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision, which is is of the heart, and taking away the foreskin, and renting the vaile, where this is not, there is no seal of the Covenant, and this ye shall eternally wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to be truth: So all to the light of Jesus turn your minds, and walk in his light, that the eyes of your understandings may be enlightned, that you may know, what is the hope of his calling, and what the riches of the glory of his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Saints is.</p>
            <p>And beware I charge you in the presence of the Lord, of walking in the vanities of your minds, having your understandings darkned; being alienated from the life of God, through the ignorance that is in you, because of the blindnesse of your hearts, and so come to be past feeling, and so come to work all uncleanness with greediness: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as you love your souls, turn to the light of Jesus, that ye may come to be learned and taught by him, who is the redeemer of <hi>Israel,</hi> the holy one, and to whom it is said, is it a light thing that thou shouldest be my servant, to raise up the tribes of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and to restore the preserved of <hi>Israel:</hi> I will also give thee for a light to the Gentiles; that thou mayest be my salvation to the ends of the earth; thus saith the Lord, in an acceptable time have I heard thee, and I will preserve thee, and give thee for a Covenant of the people, to establish the earth, to cause to inherit the desolate heritages, that thon mayest say to the prisoners <hi>go forth,</hi> and to them that sit in darkness, <hi>shew your selves;</hi> this is fulfilled in this our day, and his light is risen, which shall bring Salvation to the ends of the earth, and all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are saved, shall walk in this light; which saith to the prisoner <hi>go forth,</hi> and to him that hath long sitten in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43480:8"/>darkness, <hi>shew thy self;</hi> they shall not hunger or thirst any more; for he that hath mercy on them, shall lead them by the springs of water shall he guide them, they shall come from far, from the North, and from the West; for God hath comforted his people, and will have mercy upon his aflicted, Glory, and Praise, be unto him for ever.</p>
            <p>Therefore all people, to the LAW, and to the TESTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONY written in your hearts, turn your minds, that so you may come to know the Revelation of Jesus, which is a mystery, which in other ages was not revealed to the sons of men, as it is now revealed by his Spirit; that the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles should be fellow heirs, and of the same body, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his promise, according to the eternal purpose, which he purposed in Christ Jesus our Lord before the world began: For the outward law, which was written in tables of Stone, which was to the Jews onely, is changed, and the circumcision which was outward, and the <hi>Sabboath</hi> which was outward, and the Priests which were outward, and the Temple which was outward; these were figures, tipes, and shadows of him, who was to come; the body, and substance of these is CHRIST JESUS, who comes to fulfil the Law, and is the end of the Law for Righteousness; who washeth, and cleanseth, and purgeth by his blood, all that come unto the Father by him; for Christ is not entred into the holy places, made with hands, which are the figures of the true, but into Heaven it self, to appear in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of God for us; For if the blood of Bulls and Goats, and the Ashes of an Heifer, sprinkling the unclean San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth; how much more <hi>shall the Blood of Christ,</hi> who through the eternal Spirit, offered himself, without pot unto God <hi>purge your consciences from dead works, to serve the living God:</hi> For this cause is he the mediator of the New Testament, that by means of death, for the redemption of the transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors, that were under the first Testament; they which are called might receive the promise of the eternal Inheritance, for there is no respect of persons with God, for circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion verily profiteth, if thou keepst the Law; but if thou art a breaker of the Law, thy circumcision is made uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision: Therefore if he who is not of the Circumcision,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43480:8"/>as the Jew is outwardly, if he keep the Law, by keeping of the Law, he judgeth thee who art of the Law, by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter outwardly, <hi>For he is not a Jew which is one outwardly, neither is that Circumcision which is outward in the flesh; but he is a Jew which is one inwardly, &amp; circumcision is that of the heart, in the Spirit, and not in the Letter, whose praise is not of men, but of God:</hi> And so the Law, which is according to the Letter without, which is a carnal commandement; and the Priest-hood which is without, and the Sacrifices offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and outward washings, these hath he abolished and taken away, <hi>blotting out the hand-writing of Ordinances, which were against us, and took it out of the way, nailing it to his Cross.</hi> Let no man therefore Judge you, in respect of a <hi>new Moon,</hi> or of the <hi>Sabbath dayes,</hi> which are a shadow of things to come; <hi>but the body is Christ,</hi> who is the Light, which is risen in the conscience, which purgeth and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the Conscience, by his Spirit from dead works, to serve the living God; and this they who had the outward law did not know, as <hi>Stephen</hi> witnessed unto them, whom they stoned to death; this is that <hi>Moses</hi> said unto the children of <hi>Israel, A Prophet, shall the Lord your God raise up unto you, of your brethren, him shall you hear;</hi> this is He, who was in the Church, in the Wilderness with the Angel, who spake to him in Mount <hi>Sinai, Acts</hi> 7.37.38. so this is he, who spoke to them in Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> whom they would not obey; but thrust him from them in their hearts, saying unto <hi>Aaron, make us Gods,</hi> and so they made a <hi>Calf,</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sook the living God, and so God turned from them, and made them worship the Host of Heaven; and <hi>Stephen</hi> spoke plainly to them, who were of the Jews outwardly, who had the law outward, the circumcision outward, the Priest, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Sabbath, and Sacrifices outward, and said, <hi>Ye stif-necked and uncircumcised in heart, and ears, ye do alwayes resist the Holy Ghost, as your Fathers did so do ye; which of the Prophets have not your Fathers persecuted? and they have slain them, which shewed before the coming of the just one, of whom ye have now been the betrayers, and murderers; who have received the law, by the disposition of Angells, and have not kept it;</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43480:9"/>so these are they that had the outward law, which was given to them by the disposition of the Angels, but did not live in the life of it; and so did slay, and were betrayers of the just one, who came to fulfil the law; and so when <hi>Stephen</hi> spok these words to them, they gnashed upon him with their teeth, and took up stones and stoned him; and so all that come to witness the life and substance of the Law and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets CHRIST JESUS the Corner stone, comes to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted by them, who know not the law; for the Apostle saith, <hi>know yee not brethren, for I speak to them which know the law, how that the law, hath dominion over a man, so long as he liveth,</hi> but this they know not who are alive without the law, And as many as sin without the law, shall perish without the law; for the Apostle saith, <hi>I was once alive, without the law, but when the Commandement came sin reviv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and I dyed,</hi> but this is a mystery to the lawless and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient, for whom the law is; And the law was added be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the transgression, untill the seed came, he that can receive it, let him: But now saith the Apostle, we are delivered from the law, That being dead wherein we were held, that we should serve in newnesse of Spirit, and not in the oldness of the letter; but to the letter-men, who are onely Ministers of the letter, this is a mystery, who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know the life of the law, nor the Gospell, but are got into the seat of the <hi>Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Pharises</hi> who had the law and the Prophets outwardly read every <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> yet did not know, the life of <hi>Moses,</hi> who writ of Christ, and said, <hi>a Ppophet would the Lord raise like unto me,</hi> who spoke to God face to face, and the Prophets Prophesied of Christ, of the coming of the just one, and of his sufferings, how he should be led as a Sheep to the slaughter, and how he should be as a Lamb, dumb before his Shearers, and though they read this without them, yet when it came to be fulfilled, they were so blind, they did not see it, and so crucified the Lord of life: But now the beast is got into another colour, and now his Ministers have gotten the words of Christ, and of his Apostles, and they take these words, and are gotten into the seat of the Pharises, which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43480:9"/>Christ found them in, when he came, and cryed WO against; and here they sit deckt, with Christs words, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles words, and the Saints words; and with these they go deceiving poor people, and making merchandice of their soules, speaking things they ought not for filthy lucre, who serve not the Lord Jesus Christ, but their own bellies; and betray and murder poor souls, and do all that in them lie and spend all their strength, against the truth of God, which is now risen in this his day, in life and power, which makes them clearly manifest to be Antichrists false Prophets, and deceivers, who are gone into the world, which <hi>John</hi> spake of: And now the Light is risen, &amp; they are manifested, glory and praises be unto the Lord for ever, who is gathering his flock, which were scattered, from their mouths: for thus saith the Lord, <hi>I will both search my Sheep, and seek them out, I will feed them in a good pasture, and they shall lie down in a good fold, and I will set one Shepherd over them, and they shall be no more a prey to the heathen, neither shall the beasts of the field devour them any more:</hi> WO <hi>to the Shepherds</hi> saith the Lord, <hi>that have fed themselves, and not the flock, that feed with the fat, and are clothed with the wool:</hi> the Lord is coming to be avenged of them, the Light is risen, which makes them manifest, to be the false Prophets, and the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christs; they seemingly were all true Prophets, till the Light came, which made them manifest, by their fruits, while they were cloathed in the Sheeps cloathing, the Saints words, and Christs words, painted Sepulchres, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full without; But now that the true Prophet, Christ Jesus is risen, whom <hi>Moses</hi> said, <hi>the Lord would raise,</hi> now they appear to be the false Prophets indeed which Christ bad <hi>beware of,</hi> who come in Sheeps clothing, but inwardly are ravening Wolves; by their fruits we know them, who saith <hi>loe here,</hi> and <hi>loe there;</hi> but Christ saith, <hi>believe them not:</hi> All their practice and labour is to oppose, and persecute the truth of God, as it is in Jesus now made manifest in his Saints, they deny and oppose the light, when all the Ministers of God, which ever taught for God, turned people from the darkness to the light, and from the power of Satan unto God; &amp; they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43480:10"/>do what they can to turn from the Light, and to keep people in darkness: and so here they stand to keep people from the first principle, that leads to God; for the Light is the first prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of pure Religion, and undefiled before God; and some of them denies the Light, and some calls it naturall, and so they deny Christ Jesus, who is given a Covenant of Light, which is the true Light, which hath enlightened every man that cometh into the world, He was in the world, and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not: and so these Antichrists, and Deceivers, which are entred into the world, know him not, who hath said, <hi>I am the door of the Sheep, all that ever came before me are Theives and Robbers. I am the door, by me, if any man enter in, he shall be saved, and shall go in and out, and find pasture:</hi> but these Theives and Robbers, who are hirelings, who come not but for to steal, and to kill, and to destroy (as Christ saith) they keep from the door: and deny that by which every one enters, who are saved, the LIGHT, <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> who is the Corner stone, and rock, upon which the whole Church is built, this they deny to be sufficient, to teach salvation; they deny the <hi>new Covenant,</hi> the Law written in the heart, and call obedience to the Light, and Law of God, <hi>a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works:</hi> and so they would have the Law and the Prophets, Christ, and the Apostles to talk of, and steal their words, and never look to come into the life and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they were in; And so they deny revelation, and the Spirits teaching, and would steal that which the Prophets, Christ, and the Apostles writ, and make it their own; and so they go about to make poor people believe, who are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of God, and all truth, that they can serve God, with their stoln stuff, who is a God of truth, and a jealous God, a just, and a righteous God, who renders unto every one according to their deeds; and that they shall know one day, when they have filled up the measure of their fathers, that upon them may come, all the righteous blood, which hath been shed <hi>from Abel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and so they go on, and preach up sin, that none can be free from sin, so long as they are upon earth, and impossibility of perfection, and so they get the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43480:10"/>Apostles and Christs words, and quite deny that which they spoke for, preached and prayed for, and laboured for, which was <hi>to present every man</hi> perfect <hi>in Christ Jesus</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so all poor people, as ever ye desire to know the living God, and the living truth as it is in Jesus, or as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ye look for the redemption of your soules, turn from these deceivers, and turn to the light of Jesus, which lets you see the deceit of your hearts; this is that by which all that ever knew God was guided, by the pure and perfect law of God which is written in the heart, <hi>David</hi> saith, <hi>blessed is the man whom thou chastenest, O Lord, and teachest out of thy law,</hi> and the Apostle saith, <hi>I delight in the law of God, after the inward man:</hi> and so all to minde the pure law of God, which endures till all be fulfilled, for the law is holy the Commandement is holy, just, and good; for what the law could not do in that it was weak thorough the flesh, God sending his own Son, in the likenesse of sinfull flesh, and for sin condemned sin in the flesh, that the righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the law, <hi>might de fulfilled in us, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit:</hi> and so as ye walk in the Light, and in the Law of God, in the inward man, ye will see and know what the fulfilling of the Law of God is, and then ye will see what the Apostle said, when he said, But now the righteousness of God without the law is manifested, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing witnessed by the law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.21. so as you are guided by the eternall Light and Spirit, you will know the Law of the Spirit of life, which makes free from sin and death, and as ye dwel in the Light of Jesus Christ which is one in all, then will you come to know, and see that both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> are all under sin, as it is written, <hi>There is none righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, no not one, there is none that understandeth, there is none that seeketh after God, they are all gone out of the way, they are all together become unprofitable, there is none that doth good, no not one</hi> for they which were <hi>the Jews outwardly,</hi> being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Gods righteousness, &amp; going about to establish their own righteousness, have not submitted themselves to the righteousness of God; but Christ is the end of the law, for righteousnes to every one that believeth, &amp; the righteousness
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43480:11"/>which is of faith, speaketh on this wise, <hi>say not in thine heart, who shall ascend into heaven, that is, to bring down Christ from above, or who shall descend into the deep, that is, to bring up Christ again from the dead; But what saith it? The word is nigh thee in thy heart, and in thy mouth, and that is the word of faith, which we preach,</hi> for if thou shalt confesse with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and shalt believe in thy heart, that God raised him from the dead, thou shalt be saved; for with the heart man believeth unto righteousness, and with the mouth confession is made unto salvation; for there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Jew and the Greek, for the same Lord over all, is rich unto all that call upon him, and whosoever shall call upon the Lord, shall be saved: Therefore be not hearers of the word, but doers of the word; lay aside all filthynesse, and superfluity of naughtiness, and receive with meeknesse the ingrafted word, which is able to save your souls; whosoever looketh into the perfect law of liberty, and continueth therein, he being not a forgetfull hearer, but a doer of the work, this man shall be blessed in his deed; if you fulfill the royall law, according to the Scriptures, <hi>Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thy self,</hi> you do well; but if you have respect to persons, ye Commit sin, and are convinced of the law, as transgressors; so speak ye, and so do, as they that shall be judged, by the law of liberty, <hi>James</hi> 2. and so all who are taught by the eternall pure measure of God, are guided by the pure law, for the Apostle faith, <hi>I had not known sin, but by the law, for I had not known lust, except the law had said, thou shalt not covet.</hi> So all the Children of the Lord, are taught of the Lord, and in righteousness are they establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they are far from oppression; By the Law and by the Testimony are they taught, and who are taught of the Lord, they know the Lord to be their KING, and LAW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIVER, and CHRIST JESUS, who is given for a <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>light</hi> for <hi>Jews</hi> &amp; for <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to be the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Life,</hi> who hath said, there is none that cometh to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but but by me; the Light of Jesus Christ is the leader, teacher, and guider of all that come to the Father: The Scripture hath concluded all under sin, that the promise, by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43480:11"/>the faith of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> might be given to them that believe.</p>
            <p>So turn to the light, believe in the light, and wait in the light, to receive the promise; for there is neither <hi>Jew,</hi> nor <hi>Greek,</hi> there is neither <hi>Bond</hi> nor <hi>Free,</hi> there is neither <hi>Male</hi> nor <hi>Female,</hi> that doth believe in the light, and walk in the light &amp; is obedient to the Light, but they are all one in Christ Jesus, &amp; if they be Christs, &amp; walk in the Light of Christ, and dwell in the light of Christ, <hi>then are they Abraham's seed,</hi> and <hi>heirs according to the promise;</hi> &amp; the Scripture foreseeing that God would justifie the heathen thorough faith, preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gospel unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> saying, <hi>In thee shall all Nations be blessed, Gal.</hi> 3.8. and the Lord said, shall I hide from <hi>Abraham,</hi> the thing that I do, seeing that <hi>Abraham</hi> shall become a great and a mighty Nation, and all the Nations of the earth shall be blessed in him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.18. This is the everlasting Gospel, and promise of God to all generations that do believe, for all that be of faith, are blessed with faithfull <hi>Abraham:</hi> So wait all in the light, to know the law of God, which is just and pure, which was added because of transgression, untill the seed should come, to whom the promise was made, which was ordained by Angels, in the hand of a Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour; now a Mediatour is not a Mediatour of one, but God is one: he that hath an eye may see, and where the eye is open, there all sees, eye to eye, when the Lord brings again <hi>Sion,</hi> and the light of the body is the eye, and if the eye be single, the whole body is full of light; and as ye walk in the light, and wait in the light, and abide in the light, this ye will read and understand: Jesus said unto them, I am the light of the world, he that follows me, shall not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life, and as ye walk in the light, ye follow the Lamb, who is the light of the holy City; and as ye dwell and abide in the light, ye will come to see the two Sons which <hi>Abraham</hi> had, one by a Bond-woman, and another by a Free-woman, which the Apostle saith is an <hi>Allegory:</hi> For these are the <hi>two Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> saith he, <hi>one from Mount Sinai,</hi> which gendreth <hi>to bondage,</hi> which is <hi>Hagar,</hi> and answereth <hi>to Jerusalem</hi> which <hi>now is,</hi> and is in bondage with her children; But <hi>Jerusalem</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:43480:12"/>which is from <hi>above is free,</hi> which is the <hi>Mother of us all:</hi> For it is written, <hi>Rejoyce thou Barren, that bearest not;</hi> but this is a mistery to all dark unclean spirits. Read, <hi>Isa.</hi> 54. Christ Jesus saith, while ye have the light, believe in the light, that ye may be the children of the light, walk while you have the light, least darkness come upon you; for he that walks in darkness, knows not whether he goes; and out of the light, the way Christ Jesus, are both Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles: But the light of the glorious gospel is risen, and the desire of all Nations is come, who will shake all Nations; &amp; who will fill his house with glory, the glory of this latter house, shall be greater than the former, saith the Lord of Hosts; and in this place will I give peace saith the Lord of Hosts, according to the word that I Covenanted with you, when ye came out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> so my spirit remains among you, for thus saith the Lord, Yet once, it is a little while, and I will shake the Heavens, and the Earth, and the Sea, and the dry land: <hi>Therefore rejoyce greatly O Daughter of</hi> Sion, <hi>shout O Daughter of Jerusalem: Behold thy King cometh unto thee, he is Just, having Salvation, lowly, and riding upon an Asse, and upon a Colt, the Foal of an Asse; and I</hi> will cut off the <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot from</hi> Ephraim, <hi>and the Horse from Jerusalem, and the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Bow shall be cut off, and he shall speak peace unto the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and his dominion shall be from Sea, to Sea, and from the River even to the ends of the earth; as for thee also, by the blood of thy Covenant, I have sent forth thy prisoners out of the pit, wherein is no water; turn ye to the strong hold, ye prisoners of hope, even to day do I declare unto you, that I will render double unto thee,</hi> Zach. 9.11.</p>
            <p>Therefore this is the day of your visitation, ye prisoners, who are in the pit that is without water; turn to the strong hold, the Rock, Christ Jesus the Light; that he may say to the prisoner, <hi>go forth,</hi> and to him that sits in darknesse, <hi>shew thy self,</hi> and by no other way, nor name under Heaven shall ye ever know the Resurrection, but by Jesus Christ, who is the Light, the Way, the Truth, and the Life; who hath said, <hi>I am the Resurrection, and the Life, he that believeth on me, though he were dead, yet shall he live:</hi> So as ye desire the life
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43480:12"/>of your souls, the Resurrection of the Prisoner, which lyes in the pit, which is without water, turne to the light, and hearken dilligently to the word which is nigh in the heart; incline your ears, that your souls may live; for the Lord hath said, I will make an everlasting Covenant with you, even the sure mercies of <hi>David:</hi> Behold, I have given him for a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to the people, a leader, and a Commander; this is he who leadeth <hi>Joseph</hi> like a flock, who was dead, but is a live, whose name is called the word of God; and faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the Word of God, and theirs none can hear without this preacher, which is sent, who is anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to preach glad tidings to the poor, liberty to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, who is the Preacher of Righteousness, who preacheth to the spirits in prison; who opens the prison door, and brings the prisoner forth of the prison house, Glory, and Praise be unto him for ever, this is witnessed, and fulfilled, to his everlasting Praise, and Glory. And the everlasting Priest is witnessed, who hath by one offering perfected for ever them that are sanctified, whereof also the Holy Ghost is a witnesse to us; the Holy Ghost sanctifieth, Christ Jesus the everlasting offering, perfects them that are sanctified, the blood of the Covenant sanctifieth; wherefore Jesus also, that he might sanctifie the people with his own blood, suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered without the gate, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.12. So all people turne to the measure of the light, which makes manifest sin; and if ye walk in the light, as he is in the light, the blood of Jesus Christ cleanseth from all sin; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> here is the fellowship one with another; the Apostle speaking of those that should not inherit the kingdom of God, and he saith to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> such were some of you, But ye are washed, but ye are sanctified, but ye are justified, in the name of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, and by the Spirit of our God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. So to the pure light, all be obedient; for <hi>Peter</hi> writ to the Elect, according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, thorough the san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the spirit, unto obedience, &amp; sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. This is that by which all are sanctified, Jews and Gentiles, all that come to God by him, are sanctified by his blood; who of God is made unto us
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43480:13"/>
               <hi>Wisdom, Righteousness, Sanctification,</hi> and <hi>Redemption;</hi> this is the covenant that I will make with them, after those dayes saith the Lord, <hi>I will put my law in their hearts, and in their minds will I write them, and their sins and iniquities will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member no more:</hi> Now, where the remission of these is, there is no more offering for sin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.18. so all in the Light dwell, which is given to the Gentiles, and for a Covenant to the people, &amp; for the opening of the blind eies; for this is the will of God, <hi>even your Sanctification;</hi> and the Apostle gave thanks unto God, who had chosen them unto salvation, through the sanctification of the Spirit, and belief of the Truth, <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.13. Therefore all wait in the light, and wait upon the Lord, and stand fast in your measures, that you may sanctifie the Lord in your hearts, and be sanctified in Christ Jesus, who hath by one offering perfected for ever, them that are sanctified, and none else: Therefore do not deceive your souls, for Christ was once offered to bear the sins of many, and unto them that look for him, shall He appear the second time without sin unto Salvation: So all wait in the Light for his appearing; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you that look for Him, and wait for Him in the Light; you shall see him appear the second time without sin, and as the day dawns, the day star will arise in your hearts; and this you shall see and know, if you be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and wait in the light; and whether you hear, or forbear, you shall eternally witness this to be truth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43480:13"/>
            <head>An Epistle to go amongst those whose de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires are after truth, as it is in Jesus, where ever they are scattered throughout the Nations.</head>
            <head type="sub">Grace and Peace be multiplyed unto you.</head>
            <p>TO you whose desires are after the true &amp; living God, who is the God of the <hi>Jews</hi> and of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which is now manifested in this his day of grace, which hath appeared to all men, which brings sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; the light of Jesus, who is the light of the world, and enlighteneth every one that cometh into the world; in him is life, and this life is the light of men, which Light is now shining in the consciences of men, the living God, whose appearance was formerly in <hi>Types, Shadows, Figures, Carnall Commandements, outward-Washings, outward-Sabbaths, outward-Circumcision,</hi> and <hi>outward-Sacrifices.</hi> Now is the life and substance of these arisen, CHRIST JESUS the end of the law for righteousness, the Son of man, the Lord of the Sabbath, the light which shines in the conscience, which washeth, and cleanseth, &amp; circumciseth the heart: Who walk in the light, as he is in the Light, the blood of Jesus cleanseth from all sin, and here is the fellowship one with another who walks in the light; and so this is the Gospell which is the power of God unto salvation to all that believe, which Gospell brings glad Tidings to the Poor, Liberty to the Captive, preacheth to the Spirits in prison, <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> who hath once suffered for sin, the just for the unjust that he might bring us unto God, being put to death in the flesh,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43480:14"/>but quickened in the Spirit, is now preaching to the Spirits in prison, which the disobedient knew not in <hi>Noahs</hi> Time, while the Ark was preparing, they did not know the long suffering of God, who waited for their repentance, and so were destroy by the flood.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord God, who in times past, and in divers manners spake unto the Fathers <hi>by the Prophets,</hi> hath in these last times spoken unto us <hi>by his Son,</hi> whom he hath appointed heir of all things; by whom also he made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> World, he who was in the beginning <hi>(the Word)</hi> which was with God, which, as saith the Apostle, Was in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not; he came unto his own, and his own received him not▪ they who had the Law and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Moses</hi> that spake of him, and prophecyed of him, yet they knew him not: But now he who was dead under the Types and Shadows is alive, whose Name is called the Word of God, who lives for evermore; which word <hi>Moses</hi> taught <hi>Israel</hi> that it was nigh in the heart, and in the mouth; and that they need not ascend into heaven, neither descend into the earth, neither go beyond the Sea, but saith he, <hi>It is very nigh thee in thy Mouth, and in thy Heart;</hi> and the Apostle taught the Romans that the righteousness of faith speaketh on this wise, <hi>The Word is nigh in thy Heart, and in thy Mouth:</hi> and this is he by whom the world was made, whose light is now arisen in the conscience of the inward man; &amp; saith the Apostle, through faith we understand, that the world was created by the word of God, that the things which are seen were not made of things which did appear, but by the invisible and eternall word, all things are made, and he upholds all by his word and power.</p>
            <p>So now dear hearts, as you love and tender your own Soules, hearken and turn your Minds to this Light which comes from the word, which shines in the consciences: this is your eye, the light of the body is the eye, and if the eye be single, the whole body is full of light; this eye which is invisible, and eternal, sees God who is an invisible God, to whom no mortall eye can approach, God is the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43480:14"/>Father of Lights, the Father of Spirits, with whom there is no varyableness, neither shadow of turning; and the light comes from God, for God is light, and in him is no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness at all, and he who is the Father of light, drawes by his light: Christ Jesus, who is the life, saith, <hi>None cometh unto me, but whom my father draweth,</hi> and he saith, <hi>none knoweth the Son but the Father, neither knows any man the Father save the Son, and he to whom the Son reveales him;</hi> which Son is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he life and the word, which is nigh in the heart: And by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther way nor Name under heaven shall ever any know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ving God, and the living truth, as it is in Jesus, but by this way which is the light which shines in a dark place, and the darknesse cannot comprehend the light: And the light makes manifest darknesse; And this is more sure, which is a voice within, which calls, This is the way, walk in it; Than that which <hi>Peter</hi> heard in the Mount, which was an outward voyce, which they heard in the Vision, and Transfiguration, which said, <hi>This is my beloved Son, hear him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so now he is offered up, and now since that he is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred up, put to death in the flesh, and quickned in the spirit; and now is he rising, a Light shining in a dark place, as a day Star in the heart; and the light is shining in the dark place, where darkness cannot comprehend the light: And so all now, who teach for the living God, in this his day of his glorious appearance in the spirit, turne people from the darknesse to the light, as the Apostles did, and from the power of Satan unto God; who is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest in the light; all that love the light, bring their deeds to the light, that the light may prove them, whether they be wrought in God; the works that God works, he works in the light, and the manifestations of God are in the light, and in the spirit; <hi>God is a Spirit, and he is worshipped in Spirit;</hi> and all his Ministers, are Ministers of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and not of the <hi>Letter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So all dear hearts, turn your minds to the measure of God, which he hath given you to profit withal; the light which comes from Jesus, which is not of this world, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43480:15"/>bears witness against the world, that the deeds therof are evill; <hi>And this is the condemnation of the world, that Light is comed into the world; and the world is set in mans heart, Eccles.</hi> 3.5.11. He hath made every thing beautiful in its time; also he hath set the world in their heart, so that no man can find out the works that God made, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the end; and men love darkness rather than light, because their deeds are evill; but he that doth truth, comes to the light to be proved, and tryed: And so now this is a mystery which hath been hid from ages and genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but is revealed unto us; Glory and Praises be to the living powerful God for ever. And so give over looking out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, for teaching without you, &amp; these you call Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>without you; but know the Ordinance of God, which is CHRIST JESUS, <hi>who is given a Covenant to his people, for a light to the Gentiles, that he may bring Salvation to the ends of the earth:</hi> This is he, who is ordained of God to bring deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance unto <hi>Sion,</hi> and to ransome and redeem the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated seed of Jews and Gentiles, and to gather together into one, which is his Light and Life, which is one in all; and this takes away the partiton wall, and makes of twain one new Man in Christ Jesus, and blots out the hand wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Ordinances which is outward, and the Law of Commandements; taking them out of the way, and nayling them to his Cross; those were but a shadow of things to come, but the body is Christ <hi>(saith the Apostle)</hi> who is the light which shines in the Conscience, which washeth, and purgeth, and cleanseth the Conscience from dead works, to serve the living God: And this is he who is the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Priest, and to whom God hath said, <hi>Thou art my Son, to day have I begotten thee,</hi> as he said also in another place, <hi>Thou art a Priest for ever, after the Order of Melchisedeck, who in the dayes of his flesh, when he had offered up Prayers and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications with strong Cryes and Tears, unto him that was able to save him from death; and was heard in that he feared, though he were a Son, yet learned he obedience, by the things which he suffered; and being made perfect, he became the Author of Eternal Salvation unto all that obey.</hi> And so now dear hearts,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43480:15"/>here is your way through the obedience of the light, which shines in your Consciences, which will guide you and lead you up to God, and make manifest whatsoever is contrary to it, and condemn sin in the flesh; this is of him, and comes from him, who hath left an example unto all those that follow him; they must follow his steps through obedience, and through sufferings as he hath done who hath gone before, who is the Captain of our salvation, who is made perfect through suffering; and so there is no perfection but through suffering, through troubles, and through Trials doth the Saints come, whose garments are washed, made white by the blood of the Lamb, and so war with the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, the Beast, and the false Prophet there must be; but who loves not their lives unto death, shall overcome by the Blood of the Lamb, and the Word of his Testimony; for the Lamb shall have the victory, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, and they that are with him, are called faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and chosen: And so dear hearts be faithful to your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of the Light which shines in your Consciences, which comes from the Lamb; for all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which are saved, walk in his Light; for the Lord God and the Lamb is the Light of the Holy City, the New Jerusalem, which is from above, the Mother of us all.</p>
            <p>And so as you desire to be <hi>free-born</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> City, and <hi>fellow Citizens</hi> with us, built upon the found<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>on of the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apostles,</hi> CHRIST JESUS being the Head Corner Stone; and as you desire to be no more forreigners, nor Aliens from the Common-wealth of <hi>Israel,</hi> and strangers from the Covenant of promise; and as you desire to come into the fellowship which is a mystery, which the Apostle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced in, that he should make known the mystery of the fellowship: This fellowship is in the Light, and in the Life, and they who are strangers to the Life, are not in the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship; the who walk not in the light, are not in the unity of the Spirit, nor in the bond of peace; they who are not faithful to their measure of God, and dwells in the measure which leads to the General assembly of the first-born; they that dwells not, not abides in this measure, let them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43480:16"/>what they will from an outward form, or a profession, but the Church which is in God, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, they know not which the Apostle writ to.</p>
            <p>And so dear hearts, that you may come to know your ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation and dwelling to be in the Lord; dwell in his Light, and be faithful, to the leading, teaching, and guiding of the Lord, who is now teaching his people himself; and all the children of the Lord are taught of the Lord, and in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness are they established, and are far from oppression, but as the mind is kept unto that measure of God, which brings out of Oppression, and brings from under the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of Corruption, and from under the Power of Satan, and unto the Power of God, who dwells in the Light, and abides in the Light, <hi>as many as receives him, to them he gives power to become the Sons of God;</hi> and the day of his power is manifested, Glory and Praise be to him for ever, in which he makes all his people willing to give up freely, to be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and taught of him, who is a God at hand; and as the Apostle said to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> who worshipped an unknown God; so this God, who is a Spirit, is unknown to all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worships, and to all Professions that are outward: To all you <hi>Athenians</hi> that are outward, and to all you Churches and Forms that are outward, though they be never so like the truth, yet if you be not guided by the Light, and dwell in the Light, and taught with the Light, by which the Lord God teacheth his people, you shall never know the living God; but you hold the Truth in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, so long as your minds are not guided by the pure Light in your consciences, and the Righteous Law of God, which he writes in your hearts, Christ Jesus is the end of the Law for Righteousnesse; and his Scepter, is a Scepter of Righteousness, and where he Rules, he Rules in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness, and that which is of God, is a witness of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness; the witness of God is Just and Equal, and can admit of noe unclean nor defiled thing; but the pure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal witness of the pure God presents every man perfect in Christ Jesus: and so as you dwel &amp; abide in the Light, ye that were sometimes darknesse, will be Light in the Lord,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43480:16"/>&amp; ye that were a far off wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be made nigh by the Blood, as you dwell in the Light &amp; walk in the light, where the blood cleanseth &amp; washeth from all sin; for the Apostle saith, that God hath made all Nations of one blood and mold that dwell upon the face of the earth, and hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their habitation, that they should seek the Lord, if happily they might feel after him, though he be not far from every one of us. And so the pure Eternal Light, which leads to the Holy Nation, which brings to be a peculiar people, which redeems out of all Nations, Kindreds, People and Tongues, to be Kings, and Priests unto God, unto this pure eternal leader and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the Light which shines in your consciences, all be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; which will bring you to know the Royal Law, and the Royal Priesthood, the everlasting Priest, <hi>who hath by one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering perfected for ever all them that are Sanctified;</hi> but all that have gone before him, which is outward and visible, cannot make the comers thereunto perfect, as pertaining to the Conscience; for he is Judge in the Conscience, and he sits as a refiners fire, and hath said, <hi>I will purely purge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy dross, and take away thy Tin;</hi> and such an high Priest doth become us, who is holy and harmlesse, undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and separate from sinners, who is surety of a better Testament, and is established upon better promises, who is able to save them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> utmost, that come unto God by him, seeing he everliveth to make Intercession for them; for the law maketh men high Priests which have Infirmitives, but the Word of the Oath of God, (which was since the Law) maketh the Son High Priest, who is consecrated for evermore, and for this cause he is the Mediator of the New Testament, by means of death for the Redemption of the Transgression, which Transgression he washeth away by his blood; for Christ is not entred into the holy place mad with hands, which is the Figure of the true, but into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it self, now to appear in the presence of God for us; so Christ was offered once to bear the sins of many, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that look for him, he shall appear the second time without sin unto Salvation.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:43480:17"/>
            <p>And so dearly beloved, as ye love the Salvation of your Souls, look for him where he will be found; in the Light wait, where he will appear the second time without sin in the Spirit, who hath said, <hi>It is expedient for you that I go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; for if I go not away the comforter will not come:</hi> And Jesus cryed and said, <hi>He that believeth on Me, believeth not on Me, but on him that sent Me; and he that seeth Me, seeth him that sent Me; I am come a Light into the world, that whosoever believeth on Me, shall not abide in darkness; if you love me keep my Commandements, and I will pray the Father, and he shall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever, even the Spirit of Truth, whom the world cannot receive, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it seeth him not, neither knows him,</hi> and so this is he which is the witness of God, he that believeth hath the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in himself, and hereby know we God, because he hath given us of his Spirit; and so here is your Teacher, the measure of the Light; and as you walk in the <hi>Light,</hi> and are obedient to the <hi>Light,</hi> ye will see the mystery opened, and the book which hath been sealed with seven seals will be opened unto you, which none is found worthy to open, but the LYON <hi>of the tribe of</hi> Judah, <hi>the Lamb which hath been slain from the Foundation of the world;</hi> and who dwells in his <hi>Light,</hi> and walks in his <hi>Light</hi> will see the Seales taken off, and as the Angel poures the Violls, the Mystery of God will be opened, and when the seventh Viol is powred, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery will be finished: And so this is the way which I have set before you, which way as you enter upon it, and come into it, and walk in it, ye will know what I say; but not you who are out of this way, which is CHRIST JESUS the <hi>Light,</hi> who is the Way, the Truth, and the Life, and there is none who comes unto the Father but by him; and so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally ye shall witnesse me, if ever you know the Father or Me, saith the Son; or have fellowship with them, or have your joy full; ye will go on this way, which I have set before you, and by no other way or Name under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, shall ever any know the Father, nor Me, saith Christ; for all who are out of this way they are all gone astray, they are all gone out of the way, they are all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43480:17"/>corrupted, there is none that doth good, no, not one, and <hi>David</hi> saith, <hi>Blessed are the undefiled in the way, blessed are they that keep his Testimony, and that seek him with their whole heart. Wherewithal shall a young man cleanse his way, by taking heed to thy Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So dear hearts, wait here, this is the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Light,</hi> that convinceth you of sin, and of your former Righteousnesse which you have lived in, &amp; of your former judgment: And this which sees all the thoughts of your hearts to be vain, this is your TEACHER and LEADER, this which lets you see, this is perfect and of God; the first Principle of the pure Religion is perfect; for pure Religion is undefiled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; And so dwell and abide, and keep your minds to that which is pure of God, <hi>For that which can be known of God is manifest in you;</hi> and this is the witness of God which checks you when you do amisse, which reproves you in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, which lets you see the out-goings of your minds, into the visible things, which draws your minds <hi>to within you,</hi> which shall never any more be removed into a Corner, which will lead you to the pure way, which is called the way of holynesse, where the unclean cannot passe, which is for the way-fairing men, though fools, cannot erre there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and so in the fear of the Lord keep to this, and wait upon the Lord in your measures of Light, which you have received from him; and in his fear wait, and you will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>snes him to be in the midst of you, according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise; and when you know him that is true, then you may set to your Seal that God is true: <hi>He that cometh from above, is above all,</hi> and what he hath seen and heard, that he testifyeth, &amp; no man receiveth his Testimony; he that hath received his Testimony, hath se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to his Seal that God is true: and so wait in the Testimony, which ye have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, which shall endure for evermore; and keep your first love and your integrity, and take heed of coldness or dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and Temptations, but mind the Light which disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Temptations; and though the enemy of your Souls may present things hard to you, and let you see the way to be strait, yet who dwells in the Light, and walks in the Light,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43480:18"/>this way is free for all; and he who is the Light is Rich un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, who is Lord of all, who are obedient to the Light; but he that hates the Light doth evil, and cometh not to the Light because his deeds are evil; and he that walketh in the Light, passeth through the strait gate, and hath the Light of Life; and Christ Jesus, who is the way saith, Take my Yoak upon you, for my Yoak is easy, and my burden light; and so though it be hard, and the way strait to that which would be in the broad way, yet it is easy, and a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant plain path-way to all that dwell and abide in the Light, and to the faithful and obedient it will be joyous, and all the Commands of God will be kept where the love is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served. And keep in, &amp; wait in your measures upon the Lord, and meet together; for the Lord is worthy to be waited up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whose presence you will see amongst you, if ye wait upon him in his fear; he that waits upon the Lord shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ashamed, <hi>but shall renew his Strength dayly, and shall mount up as with Eagles wings, and shall walk, and not be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, run, and not be faint:</hi> and so, if you be diligent and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ye shall eat the good things of the Land; but if ye rebel, and be stif-necked, you will be devoured; and so wait at Wisdoms Gate, and be obedient to that measure of God, which ye have received, <hi>for obedience is better than sacrifice, and to hearken, than the fat of Ramms:</hi> So hearken to the pure voyce within you, that your souls may live, and give not your mony for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which perisheth; incline your ears, and your Souls shall live, and I will make an everlasting Covenant with you saith the Lord, even the sure mercies of <hi>David: Behold, I have given him for a witness, a Commander &amp; a Leader of the people: Behold, thou shalt call a Nation that thou knowest not, and Nations that know not thee, shall run unto thee; because of the Lord thy God, and for the holy one of</hi> Israel.</p>
            <p>And so dear hearts, as you love your Souls, seek the Lord while he may be found; call upon him while he is near, &amp; give over looking outwardly, at any outward teacher; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them who delivers from the eternal Word, which is one with that in your Consciences, manifested within from the Demonstration of the Spirit and of Power; so as you wait
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43480:18"/>in the Light, which comes from Christ Jesus the Life, you will come to know the mystery, the true and living hope which is CHRIST <hi>within;</hi> and he that hath this hope puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth himself, even as he is pure; and when you are begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten again unto this new and lively hope, then you will know this hope to be the Auchor of the Soul; then you will be no reprobates as concerning the faith, but dwelling in the pure and living hope which is within, then you will come to know the faith that is pretious, and ye will be made partakers of the faith, which was once delivered unto the Saints; which all the Saints in light ever contended for, which all the professions in the world hath gotten to talke of, but never knew what it was to be made partakers of; for the true faith of our Lord Jesus Christ purifieth the heart, &amp; is not holden with respect of persons, but in the mystery of a pure conscience: And so as you dwell and abide in the mystery, you will know the faith, which is the substance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not seen; &amp; here you will come unto the fight of Faith, and the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which is over the world, which is your faith, and so know faith working by love, and so as you dwell and abide here in your measures, and as you learn of him who is Low and Meek, you will come to see Christ Jesus to be the Door, who is the true Shepheard; and as you are faithful to your guide and leader, you will see the Theif and Robber that climbs up another way; And so <hi>knowing the terrour of the Lord, we perswade men, and are made manifest to every mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science in the sight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so the Lord God Almighty of life and power, keep you faithfull to your measures of him, that the witness of God, which hath laid long slain in the Streets of this great City <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> may now arise, and receive the Spirit of life from God, that they may prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and so the everlasting God of power and life preserve his own witness among you: And despise not the day of small things, neither sleight the visitation of God, who waites to be gracious to your souls, who hath visited you in an acceptable time: so now embrace his love, and take heed of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43480:19"/>sleighting his mercies to you: For if ever you know the eternall living God, and his truth, ye shall witnesse this to be truth, which I have written in love to your Soules; and so my souls desire and prayers to God for you, is, that you may be kept and preserved in his fear, in obedience to the measure made manifest of him in you, that your minds may be kept to his witnesse, the light in your consciences; for the Mystery of faith is held in a pure conscience, that you may be led, guided, taught and governed, by this which cannot erre, but is pure and eternall, and endureth for evermore: and if you turn from this, and do not own it to be your teacher, ye shall eternally witnesse this to be your condemnation; and when this condemns you, God is greater, and knoweth all things, and from this you cannot fly; go where you will, ye shall find this present, and then ye shall witness <hi>David</hi> to be a true witness for God, who said, If I goe into Hell thou art there, if I take the wings of the morning, and fly to the utmost parts of the earth, thou art there also.</p>
            <p>And so this witness presents God where ever he appears. And so the everlasting God of power keep you faithfull to this witness, that you may be cleansed and purged, and purely ransomed and redeemed; and so the Lord God of Life and Power keep you in his Power and Armes, who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes his Lambs in his Armes, and gently leads those that are with young, whose deare and tender care is over you, if you be faithfull and obedient; and whose blessing and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence you will see amongst you, as you dwell and abide; and so the eternall God of Power take charge and care over you.</p>
            <p>And so dear hearts, as I said before, waite upon the Lord in silence, and keep to few words in all your Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let your yea, be yea, and your nay, nay: For whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is more is evill, and mind that which checks you when you do amisse, or when any hasty words goes forth forwardly or hastily, for that which goes out of the mouth defiles the man; and so abide in the light which discovers all your words, thoughts and actions; this which makes them mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43480:19"/>to you is the light: And so wait here in the light, and you will come to know and see the Cross of Christ, which which is the power of God unto salvation, which is foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness unto the world, but unto them that believe, it is the Power of God, and the Wisdom of God: And so as you dwell and wait in the light, ye will know the Apostle what he said, when he said, God forbid that I should glory in any thing save in the Crosse of Christ, by which I am cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to the world, &amp; the world to me, and so this is the way that you must go through the Cross: So when you meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, wait in silence upon the Lord, that you may come to know the invisible vertue and life which comes from the living God, that ye may know what it is to eat of the hidden Manna. And so the Lord God of power keep you single in your measures, up to himself, that in the Spirit ye may wait to worship him in Spirit who is a Spirit: and this was I moved of the Lord to write to you in tenderness and bowels of love to the seed of God, for which my soul travels, that I may see it gathered into the everlasting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of love, life and peace, by the word of reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>From a lover of your souls, and one who waits for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the seed of God in all Nations where it is scattered upon the face of the earth, that into the everlasting Covenant the whole seed may be brought, where they may sing a new Song, M. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="queries">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:43480:20"/>
            <head>Certain Queries to all the World, Priests or others, who say the light is naturall.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>WHy was not</hi> John <hi>that light, if it be a natural light, who was the greatest born among women, who saith, I am not the light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Why was</hi> John <hi>sent to bear witnesse of that light, that all men through him might believe, if it were a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Why was</hi> John <hi>sent to bear witnesse that this was the true light, that lighteth every man that cometh into the world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>How can that be the true Light which is natural, when there is no truth but Christ, who is eternal?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Whether he who was in the world, and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not, who is the light, whom</hi> John <hi>bare witness to, whether this be natural,</hi> yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Whether he in whom is life, and this life is the light of men, which</hi> John <hi>saith made the world, be natural</hi> yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Whether the darkness may not comprehend the light, if it be natural, since the Devil hath power over the naturall of all the Children of disobedience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>What nature was that by which the Gentiles did the things contained in the Law, seeing they were justified thereby; for the Apostle saith, Not the hearers of the Law, but the doers are justified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>And whether this was the corrupt nature, which the Apostle saith, did shew the works of the Law, written in their hearts, their consciences bearing them witness, and whether that Law be naturall, which God writes in the heart,</hi> Rom. 2.15?</p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>Whether that be natural, by which God doth judge the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of men by Jesus, according to the Gospell?</hi> ver. 16.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Whether the Covenant of God, which is the light, which enlighteneth the Gentiles, be a natural light, yea or nay? seeing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43480:20"/>thereby they do the things contained in the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>And whether that which shews the work of the Law written in their hearts, be natural? seeing they did that which the Jews could not do which had the outward Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Whether the Covenant of God which is Light, be not that which God teacheth his people? who hath said, they shall not say, know the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>How shall they come to know him, and not to say, know the Lord, who denys the Covenant of Light, which he hath given to enlighten the Gentiles, to bring Salvation to the ends of the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 <hi>How shall they ever come to know Salvation, who deny the Covenant of light, which is given to the Gentiles, for open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Prison doores, and for bringing the Prisoner out of the prison house?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Whether this Light, if it be obeyed and followed, be not the way to the Father? sith Christ Jesus saith, who is the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Light, I am the way, the Truth and the Life, and there is none comes to the Father, but by me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>Whether this Light, if it be disobeyed, be not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the world, and all that love darkness rather than Light, because their deeds are evill?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>Whether this Light, if it be believed in, followed and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, be not sufficient for salvation? since Christ Jesus, who is the Light, saith, Yet a little while is the Light with you, walk while ye have the Light, least darkness come upon you; while ye have the Light, believe in the Light, that ye may be the children of the Light. These things spake Jesus and departed</hi> Joh. 12.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>Whether that Light, being sufficient to save, being believed, walked in, and obeyed, be not sufficient to condemn the unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and disobedient, and the lovers of darkness? seeing the Scripture saith, he that believeth not, is condemned already: And this is the condemnation, that Light is come into the world, and men love darknesse rather than Light, because their deeds are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>And now I challenge all you that deny the Light in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one to be sufficient, and calls it naturall, to prove by Scripture, what is it that condemns the World, since they deny the Light to be sufficient for condemnation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:43480:21"/>21 <hi>And I challenge you again, to prove by Scripture, any other Saviour then Christ Jesus, who is the Light given for a Covenant of Light, to open blind eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22 <hi>Whether the same which doth save, being walked in, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and obeyed, be not the same which condemns the disobedient, unbeliever and childe of darkness?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Whether the Minister of God, who is the Minister of the Spirit, doth not turn people from the darkness to the Light, and from the power of Satan unto God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24 <hi>Whether they be not under the power of darknesse, acting for the Prince of darkness, who deny the Light to be sufficient, and call it naturall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>And whether they be not blind guides, and deceivers of the people, who deny the first principle of truth, the corner stone, Christ Jesus the light, on which all the Prophets, Apostles, and holy men of God were built, and bore witness to?</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">Now let all the Blind guides of the World answer these Queries by plain Scripture, and the Saints practice, or else confess themselves to be Blind guides, and Leaders of the blind.</p>
            <trailer>The End</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>